Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
I came from Consort Fleur's palace
and I'm going pay respects to Her Majesty.
Will you please make way for me?
Lunar, Companion Yu will go first.
Let's go.
She just became a Companion.
Who is she showing off to?
A maid does not speak of a concubine like that.
I won't do it again.
The more you talk about a favored concubine,
the more trouble you bring on yourself.
"Forbearance calms a stormy sea."
Do you understand?
Yes.
Let's go.
Ying'er entertained Imperial Mother yesterday
with the opera song "Eternal Reunion".
I wish to give her the honorary alias Lady Melodic.
What do you think?
A well-deserved name.
Your Majesty, it's time to select a name tag.
I was told that not every concubine has served Your Majesty.
Attendant Sourire has been sick.
Attendant Chun is too young.
She knows nothing of worldly matters.
Is there anyone else?
Yes, Companion An.
Companion An it is.
My Lady, you're back!
I was worried and looking for you. Where did you go?
Where else can I go? I was visiting Lady Shen.
Hasn't the flower house always said that
they don't have such precious narcissus?
Why do we have so many today?
Deepest congratulations, My Lady!
Attendant Services has announced
that you will serve His Majesty tonight.
What?
It's an auspicious day for you, My Lady!
The flower house sent all these after this news arrived.
The Imperial Kitchen sent you Dong'e ejiao.
[skin gelatin]
We don't have too much time.
Let me help you get ready.
I thought His Majesty had forgotten I existed.
There's no rush, My Lady.
His Majesty is still working.
He'll be ready a bit late.
The servants will carry you into the chamber.
You'll wait for His Majesty lying down.
What's wrong, My Lady?
Madam... I don't know why I feel so scared.
No need to be afraid.
What's wrong?
Your Majesty ... I ...
I'm not that scary.
Did the madam not tell you the rules?
I don't like to force anyone. Maybe next time.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
Take her away.
Call for Companion Yu.
Yes.
What bad luck! We've never had a task like this.
A concubine carried in and returned untouched...
Who is singing at this hour of the night?
It must be Lady Melodic.
It is inappropriate to sing loudly late at night.
But on a second thought, His Majesty needs
someone cheerful by his side after a long day of work.
Is there a Noble Lady Shen?
Yes, we saw her at the Selection.
She's gentle and dignified.
That is who the emperor needs.
The Empress is taking good care of the harem.
Your Majesty needs to worry less
and enjoy the years granted by Heaven.
I only have one emperor,
but one emperor has many a concubine.
I have to keep a watch in case they step out of line.
I heard that His Majesty loves your Kungqu operas.
His Majesty is always busy with state affairs.
Your singing helps to ease his mind.
No wonder His Majesty is so fond of you.
What songs do you sing?
I learned "Peony Pavilion" from my father.
Do you know the song "A Gem Returned Intact"?
Only Companion An can do justice to that song.
Only she can convey the emotions truthfully.
It was a thoughtful gesture of the Empress,
but it turned out to be quite laughable.
The Empress's face will wrinkle with disappointment.
She cannot compare to Your Highness's radiant beauty.
You certainly speak with a sweet tongue.
My brother had this face massager sent to me.
It is made of the finest jade.
Using it can preserve youthful skin.
I'll let you have it.
I thank Your Highness.
Companion An has a humble birth and isn't favored by His Majesty.
Her life is over.
If I were sent out of the Palace of Mental Cultivation like her,
I would never show my face in public again.
But she's acting like nothing happened.
She is.
A mistress is not to be discussed by her servants.
If anyone belittles their mistress,
I'll ask Her Majesty to expel them from the palace.
Is that clear?
Yes. Please forgive me, My Lady.
Peace to Noble Lady Shen.
Peace to Attendant Sourire.
- Sourire.
- Sit.
Are you all right?
I'm fine. Thank you both for thinking of me.
Things will get better.
We still have many days ahead of us.
You both have your futures. I don't.
My Lady, it is still cold at night in the second month.
It does feel even colder than last month these days.
You have been doing needlework all night.
Here, keep your hands warm.
It's so cold, and yet the Household Department
did not provide enough winter clothes.
We have to make most of the clothes ourselves.
When I sent the pastries to Companion An at noon,
I saw them doing needlework too.
They said the eunuchs will trade what they make
for money outside the palace.
While ranked at Companion,
why is Companion Yu getting all the glory?
Don't talk behind their backs.
Meizhuang told me that His Majesty is
reducing the spending in the harem.
Every palace is doing needlework to make ends meet.
We are not short of money right now.
Jade, bring some money to Companion An tomorrow.
They'll need that for spring clothing.
Yes.
It's so late. Who could be knocking?
Go see who it is.
Attendant Chun! Why are you here by yourself?
Come in.
My Lady, it's Attendant Chun.
Chun'er, what's wrong?
- I was so scared.
- Don't be scared. Bring some milk tea.
Don't cry. Don't be scared.
Here, have some milk tea.
Then tell me what's wrong. Don't cry.
Here.
I was walking with Attendant Joie.
A maid's lantern caught fire due to the wind.
Companion Yu happened to be passing by in the Phoenix Carriage.
The carriage horse was startled by the fire
and jostled Companion Yu.
I saw it with my own eyes.
The imperial horse was well-trained
and the jolt was mild.
But Companion Yu was unforgiving,
and Attendant Joie wasn't very polite.
Attendant Joie has been a concubine for longer
and has a higher rank than Companion Yu.
She doesn't need to be too deferential to Companion Yu.
Companion Yu is so harsh.
She is favored by His Majesty and backed by Consort Fleur.
Attendant Joie has been unhappy about that.
They started arguing
and in a fit of rage, Companion Yu
had Attendant Joie sent to the Department of Penalty.
The Department of Penalty?
That is the detention place for servants.
How can Attendant Joie be sent there?
Did His Majesty and Her Majesty not say anything?
Companion Yu said she would hold the department responsible
if Their Majesties were disturbed.
How imperious. I've never heard of such a ridiculous thing.
Sourire, what should we do?
Don't worry.
Xiao-Yunzi.
Yes.
Xiao-Yunzi will walk you to your palace.
You had a fright tonight. Go have a good rest.
I will talk to Meizhuang tomorrow.
She'll seek instructions from Her Majesty.
Xiao-Yunzi,
walk Attendant Chun back.
How pitiful.
At such a young age, she has to live in fear.
How can a Companion bully two Attendants so badly?
What a miserable life
to live in the palace without His Majesty's favor.
Yu grows conceited over her favors and sings loudly at night.
And even gave the private order to detain Attendant Joie.
This might turn out to be a good thing.
A good thing?
Indeed. Her sudden advancement has displeased many.
She will only dig her own grave
with her reckless behavior.
You are the only calm person here now.
The uproar in the palace can almost reach Heaven.
What happened?
The Empress Dowager made an edict
to release Attendant Joie and offer consolations;
Companion Yu is deprived of her honorary alias
and will be confined for half a month.
The Empress Dowager?
Yes.
Why haven't the Emperor and the Empress said anything?
His Majesty doesn't concern himself with
such a trivial matter before the state affairs.
The Empress was visiting the Empress Dowager and informed her.
Her Majesty tempers justice with mercy.
A small punishment will teach a greater lesson.
Yes. While Yu is still ranked at Companion,
losing her alias will affect her status.
(pleasant)
The writing went smoothly today.
I'll keep this one.
Yes.
Now that Yu is subdued by her punishment,
Your Majesty can write in peace.
The Empress Dowager is very thoughtful towards Your Majesty.
Companion Yu is in high favor at the moment.
If I were to punish her,
His Majesty would much likely intercede.
Rather than weighing His Majesty's feelings against my dignity,
involving the Empress Dowager can
convince people's mouths and minds.
Your Majesty is wise.
The weather has been more pleasant
and you started to take the medicine less.
You're looking more at ease.
If things go peacefully, I don't have to take the medicine.
Since you are feeling better in your prolonged recovery,
you should go outside more and get some sunlight.
It'll also make you look healthier.
You said you wanted to have a swing
put up in the garden outside our palace.
Xiao-Yunzi has built one.
It is surrounded by apricot flowers.
Would you like to go see it?
"In the dappled shade of apricot flowers,
I play the flute till the first light appears."
You two are trying every trick to get me out the door.
I'll go then.
Vermilion, get me my flute.
Go quickly.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组🎶
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
How may I address Your Excellency?
Hmm?
Can you guess?
You can't be... the Emperor?
You are a prince?
Have you heard of Noble Prince Guo?
Are you really Noble Prince Guo?
Have you ever seen... me?
No, I have not even seen His Majesty
since I entered the palace.
So why do you think that I'm not Noble Prince Guo?
The age is not matching ...
A man doesn't always look his age.
If Your Excellency says so...
I am the Attendant from the Zhen family.
Peace to Your Lordship.
You are the Attendant who has long been sick?
How does Your Lordship know such a trifling detail of the harem?
I heard it from... the Empress.
My Imperial Brother asked about you at the New Year banquet.
I overheard it.
I see.
Has your health improved?
You should have put on a cloak before coming outdoors.
I thank Your Lordship for the caring words.
I've been feeling much better.
Vermilion, this is Noble Prince Guo.
Peace to Your Lordship.
I heard you playing "Flying Shadows of Apricot Petals".
It is befitting the garden scene.
Is Your Lordship familiar with the song?
If played with a vessel flute on a spring night,
the song's melodious sorrow would be beautifully rendered.
The xiao flute lessens the melancholy of the song,
and adds a touch of clarity
like a refreshing breeze on the snow.
My instrument was inadequate.
I hope Your Lordship will not blame me.
Your playing was excellent.
But when you were playing the line
"Fragrant spring grass carpeting the riverbank,
no further can I approach to home."
The music sounded stifled,
as if there was a sob in your breath.
Do you miss home?
“Zhou Yu could notice even the smallest mistake in the tune.”
Your Lordship's discernment rivals that of Zhou Yu.
It's been a long time
since I heard such beautiful playing of the flute.
Since... Empress Première passed away,
such music has been rare.
I don't deserve Your Lordship's flattery.
I dare not compare myself to Empress Première.
I should go back to my palace now.
I hope Your Lordship will enjoy yourself.
Go ahead.
My Lady, you're back.
Violet.
Can you ask around and find out
if Noble Prince Guo came to the palace today?
Yes.
Do you not believe he is Noble Prince Guo?
What do you think?
We can never be too careful.
Peace to Your Majesty.
- Rise.
- I thank Your Majesty.
Why are you here so early?
Your Majesty sent me the news that
you got an original painting by Wu Daozi.
My heart was itching for it,
so I hurried my way here.
Why? The painting won't run off.
A famous painting is like a beautiful woman.
You can't afford a moment of delay.
But you are never so eager
when it comes to women.
I did think about getting married.
But I changed my mind outside your palace
when I saw a lady crying like the pear blossoms in the rain.
- Su Peisheng.
- Your Majesty.
Was Yu here?
Yes, Companion Yu came here very early this morning.
She was in tears
and urging to see Your Majesty.
I said Your Majesty was not here.
And she kept crying for quite a while before leaving.
Ignore her.
Aye.
I remember that I had a xiao flute made of Lantian Jade.
Go find it for me.
Aye.
Where did Your Majesty go just now?
I was paying respects to Imperial Mother.
And I took a walk by myself in the garden.
So you had to hear her crying here in my stead.
How does Your Majesty like the lady
from the delightful encounter amidst the leaning plum trees?
Not that much.
Not as appealing as the night of the encounter.
What the mind's eye sees is always better than the eyes.
Let's go see the painting.
My Lady, Noble Prince Guo is in the palace today.
He is viewing paintings with His Majesty.
I hear that Noble Prince Guo carries an air of sophistication.
Is he around forty years old?
How could he be?
He was born in the 35th Year of Kangxi Reign.
He's twenty-five or twenty-six this year.
State Prince Heng is a prince in his forties.
He is easygoing and likes to banter with us.
What about His Majesty the Emperor?
I have no idea.
His Majesty doesn't come to the harem a lot,
and he's always followed by a mass of servants.
I am too humble to see His Majesty.
That's true.
His Majesty is always followed by a crowd of servants.
You can go. I will have a rest.
I'm sympathetic to what happened to you.
But there's nothing His Majesty can do
about the Empress Dowager's edict.
I have served in the palace since childhood.
I know Her Majesty has a kind temperament,
and never oversees the matters in the harem.
But when I stumbled this time,
Her Majesty went very strict on me.
Someone else must be fanning the flames.
Whether it was Her Majesty's decision or not,
your half-month confinement has passed.
There's nothing else Her Majesty can say.
But... But His Majesty is still not willing to see me.
That's true.
I'm afraid His Majesty will forget about you if this continues.
Your Highness, please help me!
I don't want to be abandoned
or sent back to work in the garden.
Your Highness.
Since you want to see His Majesty,
you put in the effort to make him see you.
"A request made in person is hard to turn down."
His Majesty will show pity towards you.
But ... But I don't know what to do.
Whatever you are good at, do it.
I thank Your Highness for your advice.
Songzhi, walk Companion Yu out.
Yes.
My Lady, please.
Companion Yu received a lot of favor before.
Without her, one fewer person is competing for favor.
Why would Your Highness help her?
It was the Empress Dowager who punished her, not His Majesty.
If one day His Majesty remembers her,
I will have earned her gratitude.
So she will follow me wholeheartedly
and take away Lady Shen's share of favor.
Your Highness, Lady Shen is new
and her position is not securely rooted.
Why would you pay so much attention her?
She is new.
But she was allowed to learn about
palace management so soon.
That is my greatest concern.
Stop. You all go on without me.
I'd like to take a walk alone.
But the Empress Dowager just told me to look after Your Majesty.
If I didn't accompany Your Majesty,
I would be granted death.
I can grant you death right now.
Lower the sedan.
Don't say a word to anyone.
Aye.
Proceed.
Do you want to go higher?
Just a bit.
I know you'd be afraid.
It'll be my turn to push later.
Sure, I'm not afraid of heights.
Vermilion, you're playing tricks behind my back.
Your Lordship!
Get down if you're scared.
I'm not scared. Your Lordship can keep pushing.
A bit higher.
And higher.
My Lady.
Greetings to Your Lordship.
My Lady, are you all right?
Why so shy?
You were acting heroic just now.
I apologize for my manners.
I didn't know Your Lordship would sneak behind my back.
Are you blaming my manners now?
I was passing by the garden.
It reminded me of your music
and I was hoping to hear your flute playing again, My Lady.
But today, I do not have the flute with me.
I'll have to wait until the next time.
There are many apricot flowers here.
The song you played is also about apricot flowers.
Is it because you like apricot flowers?
Apricot flowers are not as bright as peach flowers,
or cold as plum blossoms.
They are modest and gentle.
People and flowers are alike.
Only a modest and gentle person
can be attracted to modest and gentle flowers.
But I don't really like apricot flowers.
Why is that?
Despite the beautiful flowers,
the apricot fruit is sour and the seeds are bitter.
Isn't it meaningless if one's life
starts beautifully but ends in the opposite?
I'd rather be the pine and cypress,
living an evergreen life
without producing flowers and fruits.
I've never heard of such a perspective.
It's unique and novel.
I hope I did not incur Your Lordship's ridicule.
My manners were abrupt today.
I have two flute scores.
I'll bring them here for your entertainment
at the same hour in five days' time.
I hope you will be here, My Lady.
I am honored to obey.
May I trouble Your Lordship for a favor?
Go ahead.
It is inappropriate for me to meet Your Lordship privately.
I hope no one else will know
lest our good name be stained.
Since it's a good name,
who could damage it?
Your Lordship might not know...
Although we meet in an aboveboard manner,
many mouths spread gossip in the harem.
I do not want to stir up any trouble.
All right.
I thank Your Lordship.
Who is that?
There's no one outside.
What's the matter, My Lady?
We live in two different worlds.
This poem doesn't apply.
[The Book of Songs]
My Lady should take a break if you're tired from reading.
The paint on this table is coming off.
Why hasn't the Household Department fixed it?
Xiao-Yunzi requested service several days ago.
They'll probably send someone in a few days.
Your Majesty, please take a break.
Why did Your Majesty stop?
My ears were enjoying what they heard.
I don't play the flute well.
I should leave it.
Empress Première was the most esteemed flute player in the palace.
Now we have another player as skilled as her.
Is Your Majesty talking about Noble Prince Guo?
His Lordship is the best at playing the flute.
- Su Peisheng.
-Yes.
Send for my seventeenth brother.
Aye.
You were gone the whole afternoon.
Why are you back with a gloomy face?
I went to the Household Department.
They only had cold words for me.
You were just asking for some lacquer, not the monthly stipend.
Why have you gotten nothing after so many trips?
Consort Fleur is in charge of the harem,
so those snobby curs look at us with disdain.
I don't mind they what say about me,
but they disrespected My Lady.
They made many offensive remarks.
How dare those bastards?
They were withholding our charcoal in the winter,
and now won't even give us some paint.
Shh, My Lady is inside.
She will feel sad if she hears it.
What should we do? This is just the start.
We servants can get by.
But how can My Lady live with that attitude?
Huang Guiquan is playing tyrant
all because he's related to Consort Fleur!
Good Madam, Good Madam, please keep it down.
I can make do with the table
if the Household Department is busy.
It's not a big deal.
Yes.
You and I heard nothing.
Don't blame them when you go out.
Yes.
Serving a concubine like me
must have brought all of you grievances.
Why would you say that, My Lady?
I'm unworthy of such words.
I've never felt any injustice being in your service.
Everyone in the palace fawns over those hotly in favor.
Naturally, no one would have a neglected concubine in their eyes.
You must have heard some good flute music somewhere.
You can't even put the flute away.
You must have been listening to
all the flute players in the palace these days.
That's just like scratching the boot for an itching foot.
Is it that difficult to find a satisfying player?
I wonder how pretty the player is.
You're rotten to the bone.
Companion Yu, His Majesty is with Noble Prince Guo
and won't see any concubines.
You've been saying that to me all these days.
Am I a fool to you?
I am telling you the truth, My Lady.
There's nothing I can do if you don't believe me.
Can I trouble you to inform His Majesty, Mr. Xia?
I have already told you, My Lady.
His Majesty is with Noble Prince Guo
and has instructed us not to send any concubines in.
Why would you make it difficult for us servants?
I heard that Companion Yu kneeled for half a night.
Her knees softened His Majesty's heart.
Not her knees. It was her songs.
I heard that she sang until her voice went hoarse.
Regardless, she's back in favor.
Look at her go.
She was just a maid like us.
But she sang her way to become a mistress.
While we just get eyes rolled at us when claiming the stipends.
Everyone has their fate.
Yu is not even as pretty as you are.
Nonsense.
Xiao-Xiazi, come here.
Yes, My Lady.
Since you have nothing to do, shell these walnuts for me.
With your hands.
My Lady, the walnut shells are hard.
They'd break my hands before I could crack them.
Now you want to be lazy?
Aren't you always a dutiful servant to His Majesty?
What are your hands worth of
when His Majesty wants some walnut kernels?
Xiao-Xiazi, what time is it?
Your Majesty, it's half an hour past one.
Idiot!
Why didn't you wake me up?
Your Majesty always wakes up around this time naturally...
Slap yourself.
Get the coat, the coat!
Your Majesty.
You idiot!
Shelling all these walnuts...
How could you forget when to wake His Majesty?
Look at your bleeding hands.
How are you going to work now?
All right. No more walnuts. You can go.
I'm taking a walk.
But Your Majesty, it's raining outside.
That's what I'm taking the walk for.
You can leave.
Your Majesty.
Stop.
The Empress Dowager wishes to see you right away.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Support our volunteers: magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.